Marie Manning Papers, 1901-2000
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Marie Manning papers
1901-2000
1930-1945
Manning, Marie
MS 385
16 boxes (5.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Columnist and novelist. The Manning Papers consist primarily of correspondence and writings. The writings contained in this collection, especially those relating to the Dear Beatrice Fairfax advice column, offer insight into the domestic and marital issues encountered by women. Correspondence includes letters from her friend Olivia Torrence which span a lifetime; letters between Manning and her son during World War II; as well as letters from Eleanor Roosevelt, Earl of Halifax, Harold Ickes, and author Margaret Chase Smith.
Marie Manning was secretive about her age, even with her immediate family, and her exact date of birth is therefore unknown. She was born in Washington, D.C. to Elizabeth (Barrett) and Michael Charles Manning, probably on 22 January 1872. Manning was educated privately at various schools, graduating from Miss Kerr's, a Washington finishing school. Her mother died in childbirth when she was six and her father died when she was eighteen. In the early 1890s she visited relatives in England, where she "learned enough of English life" to write her first novel, Lord Alingham, Bankrupt, published in 1901.
In 1896, Manning met Arthur Brisbane, Editor of the New York World, who invited her to move to New York and join the writing staff at a "space rate" salary of approximately $5 per week. Upon obtaining an exclusive interview with President Grover Cleveland, something he had refused to the "star reporters" of the day, Manning was promoted to permanent staff at a salary of $30 per week. When Brisbane took a job at the New York Evening Journal in 1898, at his invitation Manning did so as well. She worked with two other women in what was known as the "Hen Coop," creating the women's page.
One day in 1898, Brisbane brought to the "Hen Coop" three letters from readers seeking advice about personal problems, because he believed the women were most qualified to reply. In response, Manning suggested a new column, to be devoted exclusively to dispensing personal advice. Manning and Brisbane agreed that a pen name was in order, whereupon Manning suggested Beatrice Fairfax, after Dante's Beatrice and the Manning family's country place in Fairfax County, Virginia. "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" premiered on 20 July 1898 as the nation's first "advice to the lovelorn" column. It was an immediate success, and the Journal's offices were so inundated with letters that the Post Office soon refused to deliver them and the Journal had to retrieve them by its own means. The column was distinguished by frank, commonsense advice and came to be widely imitated nationwide. Despite the "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" column's enormous popularity, not to mention the considerable time, effort and intellectual discipline it took to write it, Manning's job remained low in pay and in status, and she eventually resigned.
In 1905, Manning married Herman Edward Gasch and returned to Washington where she lived for the rest of her life. While devoting most of her time to raising their two sons, Manning and Oliver, she continued to write in her own name, submitting short stories for publication in Harper's Monthly, Collins, Ladies' Home Journal, and Woman's Home Companion. Due to losses suffered in the stock market crash in 1929, Manning asked Arthur Brisbane for a job; he obliged and she again took up writing the "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" column, which by then had been syndicated. She wrote the column until she died on 28 November 1945.
In addition to the novel Lord Alingham, Bankrupt (1902) and short stories for the various magazines, Manning also published three other books: Judith of the Plains (1903), Personal Reply (1943), and Ladies Now and Then (1945).
The Marie Manning Papers consist primarily of correspondence and typescripts. There are also photographs of the family, principally of Manning's son, Oliver Gasch (born 4 May 1906), as well as photographs of women working in industry during World War II. Letters to Manning from her friend Olivia Torrence span a lifetime and provide valuable documentation of a long-term friendship between women. World War II correspondence between Manning and her son, Oliver Gasch, is an excellent example of that genre, the more so because both saved the letters. In addition, there are short missives from Eleanor Roosevelt to Marie Manning, as well as several photographs of the two women together. Others of note in the collection are the Earl of Halifax, Harold Ickes, and Margaret Chase Smith. The writings contained in this collection, especially those relating to the "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" advice column, offer insight into the domestic and marital problems encountered by the women of Manning's time (and in some cases by the men as well). Although the column was originally "advice for the lovelorn," it evolved over time to encompass practical solutions to a wide range of problems encountered by ordinary citizens, particularly with the advent of World War II. Most of the collection dates from the 1920s to 1945, and types of material include correspondence, photographs, and typescripts of writings, as well as Manning's "featherweight" typewriter.
This collection is organized into four series:
I. Biographical Material
II. Correspondence
III. Writings
IV. Subject Files
Oversize Materials
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The collection is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions.
History of the Collection
The Marie Manning Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1998 by her son, Oliver Gasch, a United States District Judge. Oliver Gasch's son, Michael Gasch, added to the collection in 2000.
Search Terms
Halifax Edward Frederick Lindley Wood, Earl of, 1881-1959--Correspondence; Ickes, Harold L. (Harold LeClair), 1874-1952--Correspondence; Manning, Marie, d. 1945; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962--Correspondence; Smith, Margaret Chase, 1897- --Correspondence; Advice columnists--United States--History--Sources; Courtship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Female friendship--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Housewives--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Marriage--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women journalists--United States--History--20th century; Women authors, American--20th century--sources; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives, American; World War, 1939-1945--Women--Photographs
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1906-92; .75 linear feet.
  This series contains articles about Marie Manning, and photographs of Manning and her family and friends.
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1904-45; .75 linear feet.
  This series consists primarily of letters between Marie Manning and her son, Oliver Gasch during his World War II military service, and from Olivia Torrence to Marie Manning. Letters to Oliver Gasch from Michael Gasch (1944-45) were written by Marie Manning in Michael Gasch's voice when he was an infant and his father, Oliver Gasch, was overseas during World War II. There is also limited correspondence from Eleanor Roosevelt to Manning. Unless otherwise noted, all letters to Manning were sent to her at home at 1753 P Street NW, Washington, DC. Some correspondence pertaining to the "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" column is filed in SERIES III: WRITINGS because it is relevant to drafts of replies that were later published.
  The following nicknames appear in the personal correspondence:
  "Benjy" = Marie Manning in family letters
  "The Admiral" = Herman Gasch
  "Bozo," "Old Reliable," "Major" = Oliver Gasch
  "Sylvery" = Sylvia Meier Gasch, Oliver Gasch's wife
  "Old Garriffler" = Manning Gasch
  "Bobb" or "Ming" = Manning Gasch, Jr.
  "Dinky" = Olivia Torrence's nickname for Marie Manning
  "Hinky" = Olivia Torrence
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, 1901-45; 3 linear feet.
  This series is extensive and contains typescripts of Manning's manuscripts, both published and unpublished, many of which are annotated. There are also copies of two of her books, Ladies Now and Then and Judith of the Plains. In addition, there are correspondence and contracts pertaining to some of the writings, including Manning's unsuccessful attempt to copyright the pen name "Beatrice Fairfax." Writings known to have been written under the "Beatrice Fairfax" pen name are listed in the subseries Beatrice Fairfax writings; other writings are in the subseries Marie Manning writings. In the Ladies Now and Then subseries, general correspondence is filed alphabetically.
- SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES, 1929-45; 1 linear foot.
  This series consists primarily of material acquired by Manning in researching readers' letters to the "Dear Beatrice Fairfax" column, much of it pertaining to problems that families of American servicemen encountered during World War II.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, 1906-92
  - Articles about Marie Manning: correspondence, published versions, and typescripts 1942-45, 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    [See also Oversize Materials]
  - "Dear Beatrice Fairfax," Family Circle Magazine26 Jan 1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "The Soldiers Told Beatrice Fairfax," PIC Magazine23 Jun 1932 (Box 1)
    [Located in Box 2]
  - Photographs
    - Marie Manningundated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Marie Manning with family and othersundated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Oliver Gasch as a baby 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Oliver Gasch as a childundated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Oliver Gasch with othersundated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Michael Gasch 1943 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Marie Manning with Eleanor Rooseveltundated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Catherine Hollowayundated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Edith Kolbundated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Malvina Scheider 1934 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Irene Gilles and Olivia Torrenceundated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous and unidentifiedundated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Marie Manning with family and othersundated (Box 2 [oversize])
    - Marie Manning with four colleagues at the New York Journal circa 1898 (Box 2)
    - Herman E. Gaschundated (Box 2)
    - Photograph of painting inscribed "To Miss Manning, Jimmy B. WildApr. 5, 1897" (Box 2)
  - Books
    - Ladies Now and Then (Box 2)
    - Judith of the Plains (Box 2)
  - Magazines
    - The Saturday Evening Post10 Apr 1915 (Box 2)
    - PIC Magazine23 Jun 1932 (Box 2)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1904-45
  - Family
    - Gasch, Herman E. 1937-45, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Gasch, Manning (?) 1932-33, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Gasch, Michael 1943 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Gasch, Michael to Oliver Gasch (written by Marie Manning) 1944-45 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gasch, Oliver 1924-27, 1942-45, undated (Box 3, Folder 5-8)
    - Gasch, Oliver and Sylvia Meyer Gasch 1943-45, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
  - Third party
    - Gasch, Herman
      - Torrence, Olivia 1925-27 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1913, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Gasch, Michael to Sherrill Redmon27 Jun 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Gasch, Oliver
      - Keech, Richmond 1945 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Lucas, Martha 1945 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Torrence, Olivia 1913, 1938-42 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Miscellaneous 1942-45, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Friends and acquaintances
    - Coolidge, Grace 1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Ickes, Harold 1943 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor 1935-44 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Torrence, Olivia 1909-45, undated (Box 4, Folder 11-17)
    - Trewick, Kate 1944-45 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Miscellaneous 1904-59, undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS, 1901-45
  - Pamphlet: The Author's Guild of the Author's League of America," 1945 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Published books
    - Ladies Now and Then
      - Contracts 1943-44 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence with E.P. Dutton and Co. 1943-45 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
      - Publicity 1944 (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - General correspondence, A-Z, and unidentified 1944-45, undated (Box 5, Folder 6-19)
      - Notesundated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Typescript, copy 1undated (Box 6, Folder 2-9)
      - Typescript, copy 2undated (Box 6, Folder 10-17)
    - Lord Alingham, Bankrupt: review, The BookmanMar. 1901 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Copies of published books
      - Ladies Now and Then 1944 (Box 7)
      - Problems of Love and Marriage: Advice to the Lovelorn1931 (Box 7)
  - Unpublished books: typescripts
    - "Beatrice Fairfax Memoirsundated (Box 8, Folder 1-7)
    - "Child Story," Chapters 1 and 2, undated (Box 8, Folder 8-9)
    - "Child Story," Chapters 1 and 2, n.d. (carbon copy) (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    - "Crete"
      - Chapters 1-13, undated (Box 8, Folder 12-15)
      - "Supplementary Chapter on Religions" (Box 8, Folder 16)
      - Bound copy (Box 8)
    - "The Last Dragon,"
      - Chapters 1-12, n.d. (copy 1) (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
      - Chapters 1-3, n.d. (copy 2) (Box 9, Folder 5)
      - Fragmentsundated (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - "Latest Version," 1939 (copy 1) (Box 9, Folder 7-14)
    - "Latest Version" (copy 2) 1939 (Box 9, Folder 15-22)
      [See also box 16]
  - Beatrice Fairfax writings
    - Correspondence
      - Inquiries to and answers from United States Navy and War Departments re: readers' questions 1942-45 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
      - Replies to readers' questionsApr 1943-44, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
        [See also SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES--Services--Family allowances--Correspondence and pamphlets, 1943-45]
      - Legal 1944-45 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Typescripts and related correspondence
      - "Advice to the Lovelorn" column 1936-38 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - "Beatrice Fairfax is Launchedcirca 1940 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - "Beatrice Fairfax Surveys New Deal Changesundated (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - "Beatrice Fairfax Radio Continuityundated (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - "Boy Meets Girl" series 1936-37 (Box 10, Folder 9-12)
      - "Bridget" series 1938 (Box 10, Folder 13)
      - "Girl and Boss" series 1932-36 (Box 10, Folder 14)
      - "Girls Men Should Shun" series 1933, undated (Box 10, Folder 15-16)
      - "Marriage" seriesundated (Box 10, Folder 17)
      - "Petting" series 1938, undated (Box 10, Folder 18-19)
      - Miscellaneousundated (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Marie Manning writings
    - "Wounded Yanks Keep Cheerful in Big N.Y. Hospital," Times-Herald13 Aug 1943 (Box 10, Folder 21)
    - Typescripts and related correspondence
      - "And Jove But Laughs" (2 copies)undated (Box 10, Folder 22-23)
      - "And So They Were Graduatedundated (Box 10, Folder 24)
      - "Arlington As a Plantation," 1927 (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - "Asbestos Tyler's Suppressed Desires" (2 copies) 1929 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
      - "Battle Royal of Sahara and Atlantic Girlsundated (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - "Black Thursday and Black Breadundated (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - "The Case of Lillian Sabineundated (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - "Christmas at the White House," 1934, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - "Dolly Gann Best of Sportsundated (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - "Double Exposureundated (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - "The Elixir," The Saturday Evening Post10 Apr 1915 (Box 11)
      - "Evolution of a Lady," 1940 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - "The Fight Reporter Looks Over the Farm Girls, Trying to Get 'The Man's Angle'undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - "It Happened on Prom Nightundated (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - "Jewels of Evil Omen: Catherine the Great's Love Tokenundated (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Lincoln's Birthday Recalls Shop Where He Bought Toys for Tad," 1944 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - "Love Among the Sophomoresundated (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - "The Maid-of-Honorundated (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - "The Man Famine in Official Washington is Overundated (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - "Notes for 'Without Obligation' or 'Cat Eat Cat'" (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - "Numbered Houses," 1922 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - "On With the Danceundated (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - "Our Journey to the Hebrides," 1905 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - "Patience and Sorrow Stroveundated (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - "The Perpetual Providence," Smith's MagazineOct 1915 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - "Plantation Days at Arlington With Leeundated (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - "The Profiteers' Wifeundated (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - "The Prophetess Without Honor," n.d (2 copies) (Box 11, Folder 25-26)
      - "Prosperity Dawns Below Stairsundated (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - "The Ruling Complexundated (Box 11, Folder 28)
      - "Sarah Josepha Haleundated (Box 11, Folder 29)
      - "The Republic of San Marinoundated (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - "Some Further Adventuresundated (Box 11, Folder 31)
      - "The Torch Bearer 1930 (Box 11, Folder 32)
      - "Which Boy Was the Dauphin?" (3 copies) 1937 (Box 11, Folder 33-36)
    - Unidentified, "Chapter 1undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified fragmentsundated (Box 12, Folder 2-4)
    - Notebook, "Ancient Lands and Creteundated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Notebooks and miscellaneous notescirca 1928, 1939, undated (Box 12, Folder 6-14)
    - Artworkundated (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Writings by others
    - Bouve,T.T.: "There Were Giants in Those Daysundated (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - Gasch, Oliver: "Washington Now and Then 1985 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Ross, Ishbel: "Highland Twilightundated (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Author unknown: "Interview With Marie Manning"undated (Box 12, Folder 19)
- SERIES IV. SUBJECT FILES, 1929-45
  - Adoption 1938-45 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Fitness 1934-38, undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Hull-House Year Book 1929 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Illegitimacy
    - Correspondence and reports1939-43, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Homes for unwed mothers
      - Reports 1938-42 (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Florence Crittenton Homes 1943-44, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Sex education 1919-38, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Juvenile delinquencyundated (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Publications 1938-39, undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - United States Government: World War II
    - Acts of Congress 1940-43 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Army 1943-45 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Army nursing 1942-44, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Chaplains 1941-45 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Coast Guard 1940-45 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Draft deferment 1942-44 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Frankford Arsenal 1943, undated (Box 13, Folder 16)
    - Japanese-Americans 1943-44 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Marine Corps Women's Reserveundated (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Marriage and divorce 1944, undated (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Maternity care 1943-45 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - Merchant Marine 1944-45 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - Navy 1940-45, undated (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - Navy 1940-45, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Prisoners of war 1943-45, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Savings Bonds 1942-45 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Seabees 1942, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Services for soldiers and their families
      - Day care and foster care 1944, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Education 1941-45 (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Family allowances: Correspondence and pamphlets 1943-45 (Box 14, Folder 7-8)
      - Health 1943-44 (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Legal advice 1941-43, undated (Box 14, Folder 10)
      - Life insurance 1941-42 (Box 14, Folder 11)
      - Mail 1942-45 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Taxation 1943 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Veterans Administration 1941-43 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - War Department
      - Bureau of Public Relations: Press releases 1943-45 (Box 14, Folder 15)
      - Bureau of Public Relations Women's Interest Section: press releases 1943-44 (Box 14, Folder 16)
      - Reporting casualties 1943-44, undated (Box 14, Folder 17)
      - War dogs: photographs and reports 1944 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - Women working in war factories: photographs 1943 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - Women's Army Corps (WAC) 1944-45, undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Women's Air Force Service Pilots (WASPS) 1942-44 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - WAVES and SPARS 1943, undated (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous 1941-43, undated (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS (CONTINUED)
  - Unpublished books: typescript, "The Town of Glass Houses"
    - Chapters 1-3 undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Chapters 4-7 undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Chapters 8-10 undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Notes for "The Town of Glass Houses,"undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Poster: "A Report to the Women of America on our Wounded and the critical need for more Wacs in Army Hospitals" (Map-case Flat File:)
  - Poster: "Insignia of Arms and Services of the United States Army" (Map-case Flat File:)